Finding Aid for the Paul Friedländer Papers, 1848-1976 LSC.1551
UCLA Library Special Collections
Paul Friedländer papers
1848-1976
UCLA Library Special Collections
Friedländer, Paul
LSC.1551
23 Linear Feet 47 boxes.
Paul Friedländer (1882-1968) was a professor of classics at UCLA in the 1940s. The collection contains Friedländer's correspondence, notes, manuscripts, and printed items including materials for his Studien zur antiken Literatur und Kunst, notes on Plato, books, hard-bound periodicals, offprints and pamphlets from the Friedländer library, and manuscripts of his wife, Charlotte.
47 boxes (23 linear ft.)
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF. Advance notice is required for access to the collection. Please contact UCLA Library Special Collections for paging information.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Paul Friedländer, 1971-.
Gift of William M. Calder, 1986 & 1995.
Gift of UCLA Department of Classics, 1991-93.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 1470447
Biography/History
Friedländer was born on March 21, 1882 in Berlin, Germany; degree from Berlin, 1905; became Privat-dozent (1911) then Associate Professor at University of Berlin (1914); in 1920 he became professor of Classical Philology at Marburg; professor, Halle University, 1932; forced to resign by the Nazis in 1935, Friedländer was detained in a concentration camp in 1938 before coming to the U.S.; taught briefly at Johns Hopkins University before coming to UCLA in 1940; became professor of Latin and Greek in 1945; after four years was retired and made emeritus; he died on December 10, 1968.
Expanded Biographical Note
Paul Friedländer (born, Berlin, March 21, 1882; died, Los Angeles, December 10, 1968) was amongst the most eminent of UCLA's Professors of Classics.
Friedländer was the son of Maximilian Friedländer, a businessman, and Clara Schidlower. In Germany, his instructors included some of the principal classical scholars of the time, notably Franz Buecheler, Wilhelm Schulze, Hermann Usener and Ulrich von Wilamowitz-Moellendorff.
During World War 1, Friedländer served at the front and became one of the few Jewish officers in the German army. He was awarded the Iron Cross for heroism and, in 1918, returned to Berlin. During the war, Friedländer had been made Extraordinarius in the University of Berlin: in 1920, he was appointed full professor (Ordinarius) of Classical Philology at Marburg. Here, he joined the circle of Rudolf Bultmann, Ernst Robert Curtius, Hans-Georg Gadamer, Martin Heidegger and Leo Spitzer. In the same year he married Charlotte (née Friedländer).
In 1932, Paul Friedländer moved to the University at Halle. Three years later, because he was Jewish, the authorities removed him from his chair and, in 1938, imprisoned him for six weeks in the concentration camp Sachsenhausen. Bultmann arranged for his release and, in 1939, Friedländer with his wife and daughter were permitted to emigrate.
In the United States, Friedländer taught briefly at the Johns Hopkins University and, in 1940, at the age of 58, was appointed to an assistant professorship at UCLA. Five years later, he became full professor at UCLA and, after another four years, retired and was made emeritus.1 In 1968, Friedländer died.
In 1973 and 1974, Friedländer's widow disposed of her husband's books and papers. The books included monographs, periodicals, and offprints.
Friedländer's colleagues at UCLA were given opportunity to acquire books from his library. It was at this time that Herbert Hoffleit, whose library was later sold through the antiquarian market, obtained books from Friedländer's shelves. For the rest, most of the periodicals were discarded; the bulk of the collection of offprints was given to the Department of Classics, UCLA; the correspondence, manuscripts, and some books and offprints were presented to the Gifts department in the University Research Library, UCLA; and the rest of the library was donated to the University of California, Irvine.
UCLA Gifts offered their holdings to the Department of Special Collections, and these materials were mostly boxed and put into storage. Possibly at this time, one book was catalogued and introduced into the rare books stacks (Q. Horati Flacci de arte poetica epistola ad Pisones, s. 1. 1919: PA 6393 E6 1919), whilst at least one other was added to the main stacks. Some miscellaneous manuscripts and printed materials were placed in the Special Collections general manuscript file. To this file were added such other materials as afterwards were donated to the Department or chanced to be discovered: e.g., two letters from Friedländer to Carey (donated by W.M. Calder III in 1986).
1. For Friedländer, see his Argolica, Diss. inaug. Berlin 1905, p.96; W.M. Calder III in The Dictionary of North American Classicists ed. Ward W. Briggs Jr., (forthcoming), s.u.
In 1990, these miscellaneous materials were assigned the Collection number 1551 and, in the following year, the original donation in storage was introduced into this collection. Also in 1991, the Department of Classics, having decided to dispose of their holdings, donated two large groups of materials to Archives, whence it was transferred to Collection 1551. Much however still remained in the Classics Department. Some of the other materials were offered to staff, students and visitors. One individual donated the offprints he had selected. Then, the remainder, together with Five large boxes of manuscripts and offprints, was transferred to Special Collections.
In May 1992, the Chairman of Classics added an interesting letter to Friedländer from Walther Kranz (July 19, 1950); in August 1992, the original Thomas Mann materials were introduced; and in January 1993, an envelope with two photographs of Walther Kranz and a note from Paul Lindemann were found and added.2
Scope and Content
Collection contains correspondence, notes, manuscripts, and printed items belonging to Paul Friedländer, UCLA professor of classics. Includes materials for his Studien zur antiken Literatur und Kunst, notes on Plato, manuscripts of his wife, Charlotte Friedländer, and books, hard-bound periodicals, offprints and pamphlets from the Friedländer library.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Correspondence (Box 1).
Classical manuscripts (Box 2).
Non-classical manuscripts (Boxes 3-4).
Manuscripts of Paul and Charlotte Friedländer (Box 5).
Summaries of scholarship on Plato (Boxes 6-9).
Books by Paul Friedländer (Box 10).
Books and bound offprints by Paul Friedländer (Box 11).
Material for Paul Friedländer's Studien zur antiken Literatur und Kunst (Box 12).
Books and hard-bound periodicals from the library of Paul Friedländer (Boxes 13-14).
Books from the libraries of Paul and Charlotte Friedländer (Box 15).
Offprints and pamphlets from the Friedländer library (Boxes 16-47).
Friedländer, Charlotte O., 1894- --Archives.; Friedländer, Paul, 1882-1968--Archives.; Friedländer, Paul; University of California, Los Angeles. Department of Classics--Faculty -- Archives; Friedlander, Charlotte O.
- Correspondence
  - Alexander, W(illiam) H(ardy) to [Paul] Friedländer [sic],., February 10, 1942; 1.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    General note
    Removed from Alexander, William Hardy, "Julius Caesar in the Pages of Seneca the Philosopher" Transactions of the Royal Society of Canada ser.3, 35, 1941, pp.15-28. (Offprint, inscribed).
  - Alexander, W(illiam) H(ardy), to [Paul] Friedländer,., October 30, 1943; 2.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    Removed from Alexander, William Hardy, "Seneca's Epistulae Morales" University of California Publications in Classical Philology 12, 1942, pp.175-216. (Offprint, inscribed).
  - Anderson, [Mrs. Eugene], to Charlotte [Friedländer], s.a., 3.; Autograph postcard signed (2 cards), with slip identifying writer. (Box 1)
  - Arard(?), Walter, to [Charlotte Friedländer,., October 4, 1970; 4.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf), envelope (box 3). (Box 1)
  - Beazley, J(ohn) D(avidson), to [Paul] Friedländer [sic],., June 21, 1948; 5.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    Removed from flyer for Antike Kunst, 1957.
  - Beazley, J(ohn) D(avidson), to [Paul] Friedländer [sic],., March 11, 1953; 6.; Autograph letter signed (1p., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    Removed from Beazley, J.D., "The World of the Etruscan Mirror" Journal of Hellenic Studies 69, 1950, pp.1-17. (Offprint).
  - Berg, William, to [Charlotte] Friedländer,., September 21, 1972; 7.; (Cover note) (box 1). (Box 1)
    Accompanied by Paul Friedländer, "'Pre-Classical' and 'Post-Classical'" (English translation by Stanford students for "Classics 213: Introduction to German Classical Scholarship," manila envelope (Box 1).
  - Berliner, [Rudolf] to Paul Friedländer,., May 24, 1911; 8.; Autograph postcard signed. (Box 1)
    Removed from Berliner, Rudolf, Zur Datierung der Miniaturen des Cod. Par. Gr. 139, Weida i. Th.: Druck von Thomas & Hubert, 1911.
  - Berliner, [Rudolf], to [Paul Friedländer], s.a., 9.; Autograph letter signed (1p., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
  - Blumenthal, Albrecht von, to [Paul] Friedländer,., June 29, 1934; 10.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
  - B(oehringer) R(obert), to [Paul] Friedländer,., January 15, 1935; 11.; Autograph postcard signed. (Box 1)
  - Bogner, Hans, to [Paul Friedländer],., October 21, 1933; 12.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
  - Borchardt, Marie Louise, to [Paul Friedländer],., February 7, 1959; 13.; Typed letter signed (1p., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    Envelope: see also Offprints, Borchardt; Newspapers, Borchardt.
  - Brown, T., to Paul Friedländer,., June 20, 1957 (p.m.); 14. (Box 1)
    Envelope: in box 2, Friedländer, Classical Manuscripts: Unbound, "Gr. Fy."
  - Bruckmann, F., 14a. (Box 1)
    See below, Correspondence: Vanselow, A.
  - Bultmann, Rudolf, to [Paul Friedländer],., July 2, 1938; 15.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
  - Bultmann, R(udolf)., to [Paul Friedländer],., July 15, 1938; 16.; Autograph letter signed (6pp., 3 leaves). (Box 1)
  - Bultmann, Rudolf, to [Paul Friedländer],., August 19, 1938; 17.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
  - Bultmann, Rudolf, to Paul Friedländer,, envelope., January 23, 1956 (p.m.); 18. (Box 1)
  - Bultmann, Rudolf, to Paul Friedländer,, envelope., July 31, 1966 (p.m.); 19. (Box 1)
  - Calogero, C., to Paul Friedländer,., September 11, 1938 (?p.m.); 20. (Box 1)
    Envelope: removed from C. Calogero, "L'Autenticità dell Ippardo platonico" (offprint).
  - Cherniss, Harold, envelope (contained Friedländer/Oates correspondence)., 21. (Box 1)
  - Chiswick Book Shop, s.a., 22. (Box 1)
    Envelope: in box 2, Friedländer, Classical Manuscripts: Unbound, "Gr. 42A."
  - Classen, C. Joachim, to [Paul] Friedländer,., April 6, 1962; 23.; Typed letter signed (1p., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
  - Curtius, E(rnst) R(obert), to [Charlotte] Friedländer, s.a., 24.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf) envelope. (Box 1)
  - Curtius, E(rnst) R(obert), to [Paul] Friedländer,., July 16, 1930; 25.; Autograph letter signed (6pp., 3 leaves). (Box 1)
  - Curtius, Ernst Robert, to [Paul] Friedländer,., February 19, 1931 (p.m.); 26.; Autograph postcard signed. (Box 1)
    Reportedly removed from Curtius's Kritische Essays zur europaischen Literatur (1950).
  - C(urtius), E(rnst) R(obert), to [Paul] Friedländer,., September 29, 1934; 27.; Autograph letter signed (3pp., 2 leaves). (Box 1)
  - Curtius, E(rnst) R(obert), to [Paul] Friedländer,., May 25, [1950]; 28.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
  - C(urtius, Ernst Robert), to [Paul] Fr(iedländer],. s.a., April 5; 29.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
  - C(urtius) E(rnst) R(obert), to [Paul] Friedländer,., July 31; 30.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
  - Curtius, E.R., to [Paul] Friedländer,. s.a., September 29; 31.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    2 cuttings removed to Newspapers, Curtius.
  - C(urtius), E.R., to [Paul] Friedländer, Janistag Abend. s.a., 32.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., on strip). (Box 1)
  - Curtius, E(rnst) R(obert), to [Paul Friedländer], Weihnachten., 33.; Typed letter signed (1p., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
  - Curtius, E(rnst) R(obert), to [Paul] Friedländer. s.a., 34.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
  - C(urtius) E(rnst) R(obert), to [Paul] Friedländer, s.a., 35.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
  - [Curtius, Ernst Robert.] Printed announcement of his death., (April 19, 1956); 36. (Box 1)
    Curtius, Ernst Robert, see also in Friedländer, Charlotte, Correspondence.
  - Curtius, Ilse, to Paul Friedländer,., May 22, 1956; 37.; Autograph card signed (2pp., 1 leaf) envelope. (Box 1)
  - Deichgräber, K(arl), to [Paul] Friedländer,., November 12, 1957; 38.; Autograph postcard signed. (Box 1)
    Removed from Deichgräber, Karl, "Hesiod Theogonie 80-103" ca. 1947, pp.1-6.
  - Deubner, Ludwig, Notice of change of address from., October 1, 1930-April 1, 1931; 39.; Printed. (Box 1)
  - Diels, [Hermann], Testimonial for [Paul] Friedländer, s.a., 40.; Typed letter copy (1p.). (Box 1)
  - Dopp, Ernst, to "Professor,"., November 5, 1904; 41. (Box 1)
    Annotated on back by Paul Friedländer, with slip, incipit "28": removed from Offprints, Moore, Clifford Herschel, "The Oxyrhynchus Epitome of Livy in Relation to Obsequens and Cassiodorus" American Journal of Philology 25, s.a., pp.241-255.
  - Drexler, Hans, to [Paul Friedländer],., May 22, 1934; 42.; Typed letter signed (8pp., 4 sheets). (Box 1)
    See also below, Jachmann, G.
  - Fontenrose, Joseph, to [Paul] Friedländer [sic],., June 29, 1948; 43.; Autograph letter signed (1p., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    Removed from Plato manuscript. Summaries of Scholarship III (P: Peterich's Die Theologie der Griechen).
  - Fraenkel, Albert, to [Paul Friedländer],., September 29, 1926; 44.; Autograph card signed (2pp.). (Box 1)
  - Fraenkel, Eduard, to Paulus [Friedländer],., January 9, 1923; 45.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
  - Fr(änkel), Hermann, to Charlotte [Friedländer],., March 11, 1971; 46.; Typed letter signed (1p.). (Box 1)
    With photocopy of obituary of Eduard Fraenkel (Gnomon 1971, pp.634-640; photo) (box 3).
  - Fränkel, Hermann, to Charlotte [Friedländer],., January 12, 1972; 47.; Typed letter signed. (Box 1)
    Envelope (box 3).
  - Fr(ank), E(rïch), to Paul Friedländer,., April 18, 1934 (p.m.); 48.; Postcard. (Box 1)
    (Removed from Frank's Wissen, 1955).
  - F(rank), E(rïch), to [Paul Friedländer],., January 1, 1942; 49.; Autograph letter signed (4pp., 2 leaves). (Box 1)
  - F(rank) E(rïch) to [Paul Friedländer, s.a., 50.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    Removed from Frank's Saint Augustine and Greek Thought, Cambridge, Massachusetts: The Augustinian Society, 1942 (inscribed).
  - F[rank] E[rïch] to [Paul Friedländer] s.a., a.l.s., 51.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    Removed from Frank's Wissen, 1955.
  - Freyer, [Johannes] to [Paul Friedländer]., September 11, 1933; 52.; Typed letter signed (1p., 1 sheet). (Box 1)
    Removed from Jaeger, Werner, "Die Erziehung des politischen Menschen und die Antike" Volk im Werden 3, [1933], pp.1-7. (Offprint).
  - [Friedländer] Charlotte, to Mrs. Frank (Susie) Friedländer,., February 22, 1973; 53.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 sheet) envelope. (Box 1)
  - Friedländer, Paul, to Professor Carey,., July 3, 1940; 54.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
  - [Friedländer, Paul], to [Hermann] Gundert,., June 7, 1960; 55.; Typed letter carbon (1p., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    Removed from H. Gundert, "Die Stichomythie zwischen Agamemnon und Klytaimestra" TESpIA.
  - [Friedländer, Paul], to Martin Heidegger,., June 13, 1965; 56.; Typed letter (copy, extract) (1p., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
  - F(riedländer) P(aul), to [Werner] Heisenberg,., November 27, 1959; 57.; Typed letter signed (carbon) (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    See also offprints, Heisenberg.
  - Friedländer, Paul, to Herbert Hoffleit,., August 16, 1940; 58.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf) envelope. (Box 1)
  - [Friedländer, Paul], to Herbert [Hoffleit], s.a., 59.; Autograph letter signed (1p., 1 leaf, draft fragment). (Box 1)
    Removed from Plato manuscript. Summaries of Scholarship IV (F: Festugière, Contemplation).
  - [Friedländer, Paul] to [Hajo] Holborn,., September 27, 1949; 60.; Typed letter (carbon) (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    [Associated with Oates correspondence].
  - [Friedländer, Paul], to [Karl] Jaspers,., July 1, 1956; 61.; Typed letter (carbon) 2pp., 2 leaves [two copies]). (Box 1)
  - [Friedländer, Paul, to Thomas Mann],., June 5, 1950; 62.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf, draft). (Box 1)
    Accompanied by description identifying recipient.
  - [Friedländer, Paul], to [Benjamin D.] Meritt,., August 30, 1955; 63.; Typed letter (carbon) (2pp., 2 leaves). (Box 1)
    Removed from Meritt, Benjamin D., "Epigrams from the Battle of Marathon" The Aegean and the Near East: Studies presented to Hetty Goldman, New York, pp.268-280.
  - Friedländer, Paul, to John O'Ren,., July 28, 1940; 64.; Typed letter (carbon) (1p., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    See also Newspapers, Friedländer.
  - Friedländer, Paul, to [Whitney J.] Oates,., June 27, [1949]; 65.; Autograph letter signed (draft) (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
  - [Friedländer, Paul] to [Whitney J.] Oates, s.a.., [ca. October 1949]; 66.; Autograph Letter (draft) (2pp., 1 leaf + associated page). (Box 1)
  - [Friedländer, Paul], to [W.] Gerson [Rabinowitz],., February 8, 1958; 67.; Typed letter (carbon). (Box 1)
  - [Friedländer, Paul], to [W.] Gerson [Rabinowitz],., October 22, 1958; 68.; Typed letter (1p., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    Removed from Rabinowitz, W. Gerson, "Platonic Piety: an Essay toward the Solution of an Enigma" Phronesis 3.1, 1958, pp.108-120. (Offprint, inscribed).
  - [Friedländer, Paul], to [Henry T.] Rowell,., April 24, 1946; 69.; Typed letter carbon (1p., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
  - [Friedländer, Paul], to [Edgar] Salin,., October 12, 1957; 70.; Autograph Letter (1p., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
  - [Friedländer, Paul], to [Rudolf] Wagner,., November 30, 1932; 71.; Typed letter draft (1p., with draft of text on verso, 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    Removed from Wagner, Rudolf, "Zum Wiederaufleben der antiken Musik-schriftsteller seit dem 16 Jahrhundert: ein Beitrag zur Frage: Kircher oder Pindar?" Philologus 91 pp.161-173. (Offprint, inscribed).
  - [Gerhards family],., August 1938; 72.; (Postcard showing Karl and Margarete Gerhards, with infant leopard). (Box 1)
    Removed from Urkunde (Box 6).
  - Gombosi, Otto, to [Paul Friedländer],., May 7, 1940; 73.; Typed letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    Removed from O. Gombosi, "The Melody of Pindar's Golden Lyre" The Musical Quarterly 26, 1940, pp.381-92. (Offprint).
  - Gruyter, Walter de, to [Charlotte] Friedländer,., April 14, 1972 (p.m.); 74.; Envelope (box 1). (Box 1)
  - Gruyter, Walter de, to Paul Friedländer,., July 3, 1972(p.m.); 75.; Envelope. (Box 1)
  - Gundert, H(ermann) to P(aul] Friedländer,., February 6, 1953 (p.m.); 75.; Autograph postcard signed. (Box 1)
    Removed from Gundert, Hermann, "Die Simonides-Interpretation in Platons Protagoras" pp.71-93.
  - Gundolf, Elisabeth, to [Paul Friedländer],., August 9, 1935; 77.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    Envelope: removed from Gundolf's Caesar.
  - Gundolf, Elisabeth, to [Paul Friedländer],., October 10, 1935; 78.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    Removed from Gundolf's Caesar.
  - Gundolf, Friedrich, to [Paul Friedländer],., January 15, 1926; 79.; Autograph letter signed (1p., 1 leaf), envelope. (Box 1)
  - Gundolf, Friedrich, to [Paul Friedländer],., June 19, 1926; 80.; Autograph letter signed (1p., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
  - Guppy, Robert [F.], to [Paul] Friedländer,., September 6, 1948; 81.; Typed letter signed (1p.). (Box 1)
  - Guppy, Robert F., to [Henry T. Rowell] American Journal of Philology,., ca. September 6, 1948; 82.; Typed letter copy (1p., 1 leaf) (box 3). (Box 1)
    See also, Guppy, "Kircher's Specimen of Pindar."
  - Hans, Jan, to Ehrhard Bahr,., May 5, 1975; 83.; Typed letter signed (1p. with five items, including note from A. Babb; + envelope). (Box 1)
  - H(efermehr, Ernst), to Paul Friedländer,., July 2, 1906; 84.; Autograph card signed. (Box 1)
    Removed from Hefermehr, Ernst, "Menekrates von Nysa und die Schrift vom Erhabenen (mil einem Anhang über Apollonius, den Lehrer des Porphyrius" Rheinisches Museum für Philologie 61, pp.283-303. (Offprint, inscribed), with manuscript enclosure (2pp., 1 leaf).
  - Heidegger, Martin, to Paul Friedländer, s.a., 85.; Autograph note signed (1p., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    See Newspapers, Heidegger.
  - Heisenberg, Werner, to [Paul] Friedländer,., July 19, 1952; 86.; Autograph letter signed (4pp., 2 leaves). (Box 1)
  - Helm(?), R(udolf?), to [Paul Friedländer],., April 6, 1958; 87.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
  - Herter, Hans, to Paul Friedländer,., October 25, 1960; 88.; (Envelope only). (Box 1)
    Removed from Herter, Hans, "Gott und die Welt bei Platon: eine Studie zum Mythos des Politikos" Bonner Jahrbücher 158, 1958, pp.106-117. (Offprint, inscribed).
  - Hesperia Art, to "Sir," s.a., 89.; Typed letter copy (1p., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    Removed from Hesperia Art Bulletin 1, Spring 1957.
  - Hesperia Art, to "Sir," s.a., 90.; Typed letter copy (1p., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    Removed from Hesperia Art Bulletin 14, s.a.
  - Hiller, Dorothea von, to Paul Friedländer,., 27 July 1955; 91.; Autograph letter signed (4pp., 2 leaves). (Box 1)
  - Hiller, Dorothea von, to Paul Friedländer,., 18 February 1956; 92.; Typed letter signed (4pp., 2 leaves), envelope. (Box 1)
  - Hiller von Gaertringen, Fr(ei)h(er)r, to P(aul) Friedländer,., September 26, 1931; 93.; Autograph postcard signed. (Box 1)
  - Jachmann, G., to [Hans] Drexler,., March 18, 1934; 93a.; Typed letter copy in Drexler, Hans, to [Paul Friedländer], May 22, 1934 (Box 1)
    Filed above, Drexler, Hans, to Friedländer.
  - Jachmann, G., to [Hans] Drexler,., May 8, 1934; 93b.; Typed letter copy in Drexler, Hans, to [Paul Friedländer], May 22, 1934 (Box 1)
  - J(acobsthaL) P(aul), to P(aul) Friedländer,., April 16, 1951; 94.; Autograph postcard signed. (Box 1)
  - [Jacobsthal], Paul, to [Paul Friedländer],., May 1, 1956; 95.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    Removed from Offprints, Anon., "Archaeological News" Archaeology.
  - J(acobsthal) P(aul), to [Paul Friedländer], s.a., September 7; 96.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
  - Jacoby, F(elix), to [Paul] Friedländer,., June 26, 1931; 97.; Autograph card signed. (Box 1)
    Removed from Radt's review of Irigoin (Box 3).
  - Jacoby, F(elix), to [Paul Friedländer],., August 14, 1931; 98.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    Removed from Offprints. Radt's review of Irigoin.
  - Jaspers, Karl, to [Paul] Friedländer,., April 23, 1956; 99.; Typed letter signed (2pp., 2 leaves). (Box 1)
  - Justesen, P. Th., to "Sir,"., September 1925; 100.; mimeograph (1p., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    Removed from Offprints, Justesen, [Le mot "galimatias"].
  - Kaehler, Siegfried A., to [Paul] Friedländer,., Dec. 14, 1959; 101.; Typed letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
  - Kalitsunakis, Job., to Paul Friedländer,., November 12, 1932 (p.m.); 102.; Envelope. (Box 1)
  - Karpp, Heinrich, to [Paul Friedländer],., August 14, 1934; 103.; Autograph letter signed (2pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)
    Removed from Karpp, Heinrich, "Sorans vier Bücher ?EPI ?YXHS und Tertullians schrift De anima" Zeitschrift für die neutestamentliche Wissenschaft und die Kunde der älteren Kirche 33, 1934, pp.31-47 (offprint).
  - Keydell, R[udolf], to Herr Professor,., January 26, 1930; 104.; Autograph letter signed (3pp., 1 leaf). (Box 1)